Waleed Iqbal

Email: waleediqbal411@gmail.com Web: www.waleediqbal.info LinkedIn: waleediqbal411 Tel: +447515669562

SHORT BIO

I have experience of teaching and cutting-edge research in prestigious institutes including Queen Mary University of London (UK) and Information Technology University (Pakistan). As Teaching Fellow at QMUL, I lectured one UG Degree Apprenticeship course: IOT524U (56 students), and co-lectured two UG courses: ECS524U (425 students) and ECS417U (322 students). I regularly employ student-centric and active learning approaches during my lectures. I have also authored (and co-authored) more than 13 research papers in leading peer-reviewed international journals and conference proceedings. Out of those, six papers are 4* REF papers and seven papers are 3* REF papers. I regularly publish in top-tier research venues such as AAAI ICWSM and ACM IMC. For my research and teaching accomplishments, I have been granted UK's Global Talent Visa (Exceptional Promise) in Research and Academic Category.

EXPERIENCE

Teaching Fellow, Queen Mary University of London, UK

September 2022–Present

- Module lecturer for IOT524U (UG Degree Apprenticeship) and ECS524U (co-lecturer, UG) Internet Protocols and Applications.
- Module co-lecturer for ECS417U Fundamentals of Web Technologies.
- MSc Final Dissertation Supervision in School of EECS
- Undergraduate Project Supervision in School of EECS

Consultant, Machine Learning, Ibtidah Solutions Ltd., Lahore, Pakistan March 2020–March 2023

- Consultancy for Machine Learning team building.
- Advising Machine Learning team on data analytics and model design.
- Strategic recommendations for client's system design.

Lab Demonstrator, Queen Mary University of London, UK

September 2020–September 2022

• Courses Assisted: ECS607U/ECS766P Data Mining (UG, PG), ECS417U Fundamentals of Web Technologies (UG), ECS781A/P Cloud Computing (PG), ECS780P Computer Programming (UG), ECS637U/ECS757P Digital Media and Social Networks (UG, PG).

Research Associate, IT University Lahore, Pakistan Projects:

November 2015-December 2019

- Scientometric Analysis of Computer Networking Research.
- Evaluation Study of link quality in 802.15.4 Zigbee Protocol.
- Performance evaluation of Educational Volunteers in Government School.

Teaching Assistant, IT University Lahore, Pakistan

November 2015–December 2019

• Courses Assisted: Computer Networking (UG), Operating Systems (UG), Data Structures (UG), Object Oriented Programming (UG), Advanced Operating Systems (PG), Advanced Topics in Artificial Intelligence (PG).

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Computer Science, Queen Mary University of London, UK

Thesis submission by Aug 2024

- Thesis: Exploring online manifestation of real-world inequalities.
- Funded By: Queen Mary Postgraduate Research Studentships

M.S. Computer Science, IT University Lahore, Pakistan

Nov 2015–June 2018

- Thesis: Analysis of Computer Networking Research: A Bibliometric Study.
- Funded By: Information Technology University Graduate Student Fellowship.

B.Sc. Electrical Engineering, University of the Punjab, Pakistan.

December 2009–April 2014

• Dissertation: Analysis of VoIP Structure and Standards: Deployment of an Open Source VoIP Network for an Organization with Enhanced Services.

SELECTED **PUBLICATIONS**

Full list of publications can be found on my Google Scholar Page.

- [1] Iqbal, Waleed, Vahid Ghafouri, Gareth Tyson, Guillermo Suarez-Tangil, and Ignacio Castro. "Lady and the Tramp Nextdoor: Online Manifestations of Real-World Inequalities in the Nextdoor Social Network." In Proceedings of the International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM) 2023.
- [2] Iqbal, Waleed, Gareth Tyson, Vahid Ghafouri, Guillermo Suarez-Tangil, and Ignacio Castro. "Exploring online manifestations of real-world inequalities." In Proceedings of the 22nd ACM Internet *Measurement Conference (IMC)* **2022** (Poster).
- [3] Javed, R. Tallal, Muhammad Usama, Waleed Iqbal, Junaid Qadir, Gareth Tyson, Ignacio Castro, and Kiran Garimella. "A deep dive into COVID-19-related messages on WhatsApp in Pakistan." Social Network Analysis and Mining 2022.
- [4] Latif, Siddique, Muhammad Usman, Sanaullah Manzoor, Waleed Iqbal, Junaid Qadir, Gareth Tyson, Ignacio Castro, Adeel Razi, Maged N. Kamel Boulos, Adrian Weller, and Jon Crowcroft. "Leveraging data science to combat COVID-19: A comprehensive review." IEEE Transactions on Artificial Intelligence 2020.
- [5] Iqbal, Waleed, Junaid Qadir, Saeed-Ul Hassan, Rana Tallal Javed, Adnan Noor Mian, Jon Crowcroft, and Gareth Tyson. "Five decades of the ACM special interest group on data communications (SIG-COMM) a bibliometric perspective." ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review 2019 (Technical Editorial).
- [6] Iqbal, Waleed, Junaid Qadir, Gareth Tyson, Adnan Noor Mian, Saeed-ul Hassan, and Jon Crowcroft. "A bibliometric analysis of publications in computer networking research." Scientometrics 2019.

GRANTS AND **AWARDS**

Global Talent Visa (Exceptional Talent in Research and Academic Category), United Kingdom 2023 Travel Grant, Oxford LLM Workshop, Department of Sociology, University of Oxford 2023

Travel Grant, ACM Internet Measurement Conference, Nice, France 2022 Queen Mary Principal PhD Studentship, Queen Mary University of London, UK 2020

Dean's Roll of Honor for MS Computer Science, IT University Lahore, Pakistan 2018

Graduate Student Fellowship, IT University Lahore, Pakistan 2015

Dean's Roll of Honor for BSc Electrical Engineering, University of The Punjab, Pakistan 2014

Courses

PROFESSIONAL Natural Language Processing with Classification and Vector Spaces, Coursera Mar 2023 TRAINING AND Version Control, Coursera Aug 2023

Neural Network and Deep Learning, Coursera

Sep 2017

TECHNICAL

Programming Python, C++, C Language, and Javascript.

SKILLS

Technical Tools Jupyter Notebook, Tableau, Telerik Fiddler, Gephi, SPSS, Git, and Postman API Platform.

ACADEMIC SERVICES

Reviewer AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM) 2023 **Shadow TPC Member** ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC) 2022

Reviewer ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review (CCR) 2019

REFERENCES

Dr. Ignacio Castro, Lecturer, Queen Mary University of London, UK

PhD advisor

email: i.castro@gmul.ac.uk

Prof. Gareth Tyson, Professor, Queen Mary University of London, UK

PhD co-advisor

email: g.tyson@qmul.ac.uk